[Music]
in the last section our study of routing was primarily theoretical took a look
at routing algorithms both centralized and distributed for computing minimum cost paths from source
to destination in this section and the next we're going to look at putting
these principles into practice i'm going to start by looking at two particular considerations
scale and autonomy that are really important in putting these principles into practice for
scale how do we do routing when
for scale how do we do routing when
there are literally billions of endpoints to be routed to autonomy has to do
with allowing network managers and operators to choose how routing's done both within their
own network and how routing is done to distant networks as well we're going
to cover two routing protocols here the open shortest path first ospf routing algorithm
routing protocol for controlling routing within a network then we're also going to cover
in the following section the border gateway protocol bgp for routing among networks so
why don't we get started and we're going to start with looking at this
issue of scale and also autonomy our study of routing algorithms so far has
been pretty idealized we've considered the network as sort of a sea of indistinguishable
routers that were connected by links we simply wanted to find a shortest path
from a source router to a destination
router
well in practice things are a little bit
more complicated than that
and they're complicated primarily by the
issue of scale
how is it that we can route to literally
billions of n-hosts and hundreds of
thousands
of destination networks if you think
about it a router's forwarding table
couldn't possibly hold a billion
forwarding entries for all of the
destination hosts
and similarly when we think about a
routing algorithm exchanging
distance vector or link state
information literally with
millions of other entities just isn't
scalable use up all the bend within the
network
just for control purposes
and then there's the issue of autonomy
and this might be a little less
obvious remember the internet is a
network of networks and
each network has an owner operator to
what extent
can or should that network owner
operator be
told how to route traffic what autonomy
does a network have with respect to its
routing
we'll see that the internet approach is
twofold first
a network can choose to use whatever
routing protocol it wants
in its own network and secondly a
network will be able to control how
traffic from its customer networks
is routed towards a destination and how
it as a network
routes traffic that it carries that's
sent to it by other networks
well let's begin with the issue of
scaling
the internet approach to scaling routing
begins with the notion of
aggregating routers into networks or
into regions that are sometimes called
autonomous systems or domains and as
we'll see
there's basically two types of routing
there's routing protocols for routing
within a domain
and there are routing protocols for
routing among domains
and as we'll see there are different
protocols for each
and let's start with the notion of
routing within a network within
an autonomous system this is known as
intra
domain routing and in in trunk domain
routing
all routers within the domain within the
autonomous system within the network
are all executing the same routing
protocols
but different networks different
autonomous systems can choose
their own intra domain routing protocol
and as we'll see the edge of every
autonomous system
is a specialized type of router known as
a gateway
that will connect one autonomous system
to another
and then there's inter-as otherwise
known as
inter domain routing for routing among
autonomous systems
here a network's gateway is going to
perform inter domain routing
as well as participate in intra domain
routing
within its own autonomous system here's
a network with three autonomous systems
as1 as2 and as3
three interconnected networks each as
has its own
intra-domain routing protocol each as
could use a
different intra-domain routing protocol
it doesn't really matter
to the other asses since that as is
just routing within intra-domain and we
see here the inter
autonomous system routing protocol
that's responsible for routing between
and
among domains the intra domain routing
protocol will be used to populate
a router's forwarding table for
destinations within the network
but what about traffic destined to
outside the network
it's here that the inter-as inter-domain
routing protocol
and a bit of the intra-as routing
protocol will be used to populate a
router's forwarding table
for destinations outside the network but
let's start with the case of routing and
forwarding to destinations within
the as since that's a bit easier there
have only been
three intra domain routing protocols
that have been adopted in practice
the first is the routing information
protocol simply known as rip rip
was invented in the early 1980s and
standardized in rfc
1723 it's a classic distance vector
protocol where distance vector protocols
are exchanged periodically every 30
seconds
it was used widely in the 80s the 90s
and into the oos
but rip was eventually overtaken as an
intra-domain routing protocol
by the open shortest path first or ospf
protocol ospf is a classic link state
protocol that uses dijkstra's algorithm
to compute shortest paths
there's a related protocol known as isis
intermediate system to intermediate
system routing that's
very similar almost identical to ospf
but standardized by the international
standards organization
iso rather than the ietf and in just a
second we're going to take a little bit
closer look
at ospf because really right now it's
the most
widely deployed intra domain routing
protocol in practice
the third commonly deployed intra-as
routing protocol
is eigrp the enhanced interior gateway
it's also distance vector based and
actually it was
formerly proprietary within cisco for
decades you couldn't actually
figure out exactly what was in eigrp
however in 2013 cisco open sourced eigrp
and it became an open protocol now let's
take a look at the ospf
open shortest path first routing
protocol
on ospf stands for open meaning that the
specifications
publicly available ospf is a classic
link state protocol each router is going
to flood ospf
link state advertisements across the
entire autonomous system
that is each ospf router is going to
flood
information about each of its attached
links that will propagate to
all other routers in the autonomous
system and so
as in a classic link state algorithm
each router has
full topology information ospf then uses
dijkstra-like algorithm to compute each
forwarding table
multiple link cost metrics are possible
the amount of bandwidth available the
delay associated with the link are two
examples of link cost metrics
and finally one of the most recent
innovations in ospf
really a needed innovation is that all
ospf messages
are authenticated ospf can also
operate in what's called a hierarchical
mode ospf hierarchies have
two levels there's a local area you can
see here in the figure
three areas area one two and three as
well as a backbone
and ling state advertisements as part of
the classic link state algorithm
are now only going to be flooded within
an area
or within a backbone so you can see how
this hierarchical structure is going to
scope the amount of information that
flows
among the routers in the entire
hierarchical network
each node is going to have detailed
information about the
full topology within its area or within
its backbone
so the question is how do you know how
to route to
other nodes that are not part of your
area or not in the backbone
this is the role of the area border
routers an area border router is going
to summarize distances
to other destinations in its own area
and advertise this to other nodes in the
backbone
the local routers in an area are going
to perform just like classic
link state algorithms they're going to
flood link state information
within the area they're going to compute
routing within the area
and they're going to forward packets
that need to go outside the area
to the area border router in the
backbone we see
two types of routers we see a boundary
router that's going to connect this
hierarchical ospf network to the larger
outside world to connect to other
autonomous systems and then within the
backbone there are backbone routers that
are going to run ospf they're going to
flood link state information but will do
so only within the backbone
well that wraps up the first of our two
sections on the practice of
internet routing protocols we saw how
the issues of
scale and autonomy are really important
considerations in designing
how internet routing works we took a
look at one
in tri domain routing protocol the open
shortest path first
ospf protocol that's widely used in the
internet today
coming up in the next section we're
going to take a look at an inter
domain routing protocol the border
gateway protocol
bgp there's only one inter domain
routing protocol
in use in the internet and for that
reason bgp is sometimes referred to as
the glue
that holds the internet together because
it's bgp
that determines how routing is done
among  separate autonomous systems